<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="0.91">
<channel>
<title>WWF - Environmental News</title>
<description>News, publications and job feeds from WWF - the global conservation organization </description>
<language>en</language>
<managingEditor>no_reply@panda.org (WWF - No Reply)</managingEditor>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/news</link>
<image>
<title>WWF - Environmental News</title>
<width>70</width>
<height>93</height>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/news</link>
<url>https://wwf.panda.org/img/rsschannellogo.jpg</url>
</image>
<item>
<title>World may reach in 1.5°C in one of the next 5 years if urgent action is not taken to reduce emissions</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=2670441</link>
<description> (27 May 2021) - The global temperature has about a 40% chance of temporarily reaching 1.5°C in at least one of the next five years, according to a new climate update issued by the World Meteorological Organization (WMO).
At least one year between 2021-2025 has a 90% likelihood of becoming the warmest on record, which would dislodge 2016 from the top ranking, according to the United Kingdom’s Met Office, the WMO’s lead centre for such predictions.
In 2020 – one of the three warmest years on record – the global average temperature was 1.2 °C above the pre-industrial baseline. It highlighted the acceleration in climate change indicators like rising sea levels, melting sea ice, and extreme weather, as well as worsening impacts on socio-economic development.
Manuel Pulgar-Vidal, WWF Global Lead Climate &amp; Energy said, “Every half a degree matters, to people, to nature, and to our planet. With urgent, scaled actions that sharply reduce greenhouse gas emissions it is possible to keep global warming to 1.5°C. We cannot afford to slide backwards on this. The international community must lay the foundations committing to structural policy action at the G7 meeting in the UK in June, at the G20 in October in Italy and, crucially, at the COP26 climate talks in Glasgow in November. If they do so, the world’s leaders have an opportunity to make 2021 the year we turned the corner on rising global temperatures,” he said.
Dr Stephen Cornelius, WWF-UK Chief Adviser – Climate Change said, “Limiting global warming to 1.5C is of critical importance to prevent the worst impacts of the climate crisis on people and nature, but we know without global action we are at risk of reaching this threshold in the coming years. With so much at stake, Governments must take urgent action to cut greenhouse gas emissions and restore nature, as these are essential steps to keep global temperature rises in check.”
Prof Petteri Taalas, WMO Secretary General said “These are more than just statistics. Increasing temperatures mean more melting ice, higher sea levels, more heatwaves and other extreme weather, and greater impacts on food security, health, the environment and sustainable development. This study shows – with a high level of scientific skill – that [the world] is getting measurably and inexorably closer to the lower target of the Paris Agreement on Climate Change. It is yet another wakeup call that the world needs to fast-track commitments to slash greenhouse gas emissions and achieve carbon neutrality.”
Notes to editors:
The latest predictions suggest that:
Annual mean global (land and sea) mean near-surface temperature is likely to be at least 1°C warmer than pre-industrial levels (defined as the 1850-1900 average) in each of the coming 5 years and is very likely to be within the range 0.9 – 1.8°C;
It is about as likely as not (40% chance) that one of the next 5 years will be at least 1.5°C warmer than pre-industrial levels and the chance is increasing with time;
It is very unlikely (10%) that the 5 year5-year mean annual global near-surface temperature for 2021-2025 will be 1.5°C warmer than pre-industrial levels;
The chance of at least one year exceeding the current warmest year, 2016, in the next five years is 90%;
Over 2021-2025, almost all regions, except parts of the southern oceans and the North Atlantic are likely to be warmer than the recent past (defined as the 1981-2010 average);
Over 2021-2025, high latitude regions and the Sahel are likely to be wetter than the recent past;
Over 2021-2025 there is an increased chance of more tropical cyclones in the Atlantic compared to the recent past;
In 2021, large land areas in the Northern Hemisphere are likely to be over 0.8°C warmer than the recent past;
In 2021, the Arctic (north of 60°N) is likely to have warmed by more than twice as much as the global mean compared to the recent past;
In 2021, southwestern North America is likely to be drier than the recent past whereas the Sahel region and Australia are likely to be wetter.
For further information contact Mandy Jean Woods mwoods@wwfint.org
</description>
<dc:date>2021-05-27T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Proposed energy policy sees Asian Development Bank ending funding for coal-fired power plants, but keeps options open to fund gas</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=2441966</link>
<description> (13 May 2021) - The Asian Development Bank has announced it will end funding for new coal-fired power plants, but kept gas in its portfolio of fundable activities, calling it a ‘transition fuel’.
Developing Member Countries (DMCs) in the region contribute 45% of global energy sector greenhouse gas emissions. For Asia to become truly sustainable, “economic development must be rapidly decoupled from its high dependence on curbing fossil-fuel use,” the bank said in its updated draft Energy Policy, released earlier this month for public comment. It will be presented to its Board in October 2021 for approval.
Vanessa Perez-Cirera, WWF Global Deputy Lead Climate &amp; Energy said: “Given the urgent need to reduce greenhouse gas emissions, public funding, whether through multilateral development banks or other development finance institutions, should no longer be used for fossil fuel-based energy supply.” She said climate science clearly shows that keeping average global warming within a maximum increase of 1.5°C demands rapid movement of the global economy to a future powered by sustainable, renewable energy.
David McCauley, WWF Senior Vice President and Global Lead for Public Sector Partnerships, said, “While the proposed shift away from funding “new coal-fired capacity” supports what scientists say we must do, but it does not go far enough to help align the Asia-Pacific region to a path to staying within the 1.5°C global temperature goal of the Paris Agreement.”
The bank must forswear all investments tied to fossil fuel-based power, he said.
By adopting this wider policy, instead of enabling fossil fuel dependencies, ADB can build on its already substantial financing for solar and wind power, energy efficiency improvements, and other investments and support a consistent, rapid transition of the region to a clean and renewable energy future, said McCauley.
For further information, contact Mandy Jean Woods mwoods@wwfint.org
</description>
<dc:date>2021-05-13T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Shipping industry U-turn on carbon pricing long overdue</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=2290441</link>
<description> (27 April 2021) - The shipping industry’s leading global lobby group the International Chamber of Shipping (ICS) last weekendedits years-long opposition to carbon pricing.
It is imperative now that ICS and other sponsors should withdraw theirIMRB proposalto allow time for discussion on carbon pricing, and support the far more serious and ambitious proposal for a $100/mt carbon price already on the table.
As advocates of climate and public health action, we note this U-turn as long overdue on the road to decarbonizing the shipping industry - which at 1 billion tonnes of carbon dioxide (CO2)emissions a year and rising, is one of the world’s top ten largest polluters of the earth’s climate.
ICS Secretary-General Guy Platten, isreportedas saying that a“realization that everything has to be done in parallel”,from producing sustainable fuels and building bunker infrastructure to new engine technology, is behind the shift in ICS’s position. Many of our organizations have been explaining patiently over the last decade or so that all of these changes across the industry have to happen in parallel. So we welcome this realization, even if it’s taken much longer than the science of planetary warming needed.
After its U-turn, ICS is now “calling on world leaders” to urgently examine the role of carbon pricing for the global shipping industry, and prioritize discussion of this topic.
We share this sentiment, but must point out the main obstacle to world leaders (or indeed any countries) discussing this topic is ICS’s own proposal for a meagre $2/mt levy on bunker fuel. Instead of discussing carbon pricing, ICS has, since 2019, been pushing for this minimal $2/mt levy on bunker fuel sold (equivalent to $0.67/tonne CO2), in order to fund an International Maritime Research Board (IMRB) to be housed at the United Nations shipping body, the International Maritime Organization (IMO).
The IMRB proposal would take up most available bandwidth for discussion at IMO over the next few years - when, as ICS now agrees, we should urgently be designing and implementing a carbon pricing system, as well as developing new measures to urgently cut shipping’s climate impact in the short-term.
To show their seriousness of intent about prioritizing carbon pricing discussions, ICS and other sponsors should officially withdraw their IMRB proposal to free up space in the IMO’s calendar.
Failing that, they should acknowledge the far more serious and ambitious proposal for a $100/mt carbon levy, submitted by the Marshall Islands and Solomon Islands, and merge their IMRB ideas into that. Indeed, there is no need to “bring forward” the discussions - this concrete proposal is on the table and will be discussed in the IMO’s June meeting. We look forward to hearing industry support for it.
This press release is issued by:
Environmental Defense Fund:Aoife O’Leary -aoleary@edf.org
Transport &amp; Environment:Faig Abbasov -faig.abbasov@transportenvironment.org
Pacific Environment:Madeline Rose -mrose@pacificenvironment.org
Carbon Market Watch:Sam Van den plas - sam.vandenplas@carbonmarketwatch.org
WWF International:Mark William Lutes -marklutes@wwf.org.br
NOTES TO EDITORS
Background:Carbon pricing has been at the centre of economic thinking about how to reduce emissions in the most cost-effective manner for many years. China this Februarylaunchedthe world’s largest carbon market, for its power sector. TheEU’s Emissions Trading Schemewas the first major carbon market, and has successfully helped reduce power sector and industrial emissions. California, the world’s fifth-largest economy, establishedits emissions trading programin 2013, and current U.S. Treasury Secretary Janet Yellen has spoken in support of a carbon price for the USA starting at $40/tonne and rising over time. Many other countries have implemented carbon pricing to control emissions, including Canada which has mandated a carbon price which will reach $170 per tonne by 2030.
What happens next?Governments will meet virtually at the 76th Marine Environment Protection Committee (“MEPC76”) this June 10-17. The key choice for governments is whether to take forward in some form the Marshall Islands and Solomon Islands’ serious and ambitious proposal for a$100/mt carbon levy, or instead to prioritize discussion of ICS’ (and other industry groups)IMRB proposalfor a $0.67 per tonne of CO2equivalent levy ($2/mt per tonne of bunker fuel) - over 100 times less ambitious.
As well as starting discussions of Mid-Term Measures such as carbon pricingat the June meeting,governments are expected to approve an extremely weak package of Short-Term Measures(the result of three years of negotiation since the Initial Strategy), that have the following flaws:
No carbon intensity target, and a weakened Energy Efficiency of Existing Ships Index (EEXI):The proposal still contains no carbon intensity target compatible with 1.5ºC trajectory, and reduces the stringency of the required EEXI for many ship types.
Loopholes: non-compliant ships will be able to continue underperforming for three consecutive years before they even have to file a plan to make improvements, and can easily dodge the rules and continue underperforming indefinitely by ensuring one compliant year every three years.
No actual enforcement: All clauses that would create consequences for non-compliance - such as increased EEXI stringency, or ultimately revoking a ship’s statement of compliance - have been removed. CSC and Pacific Environment’s moderate enforcement proposal (of limiting time at sea in the following year, in proportion to non-compliance) - has been excluded.
These purposefully designed weaknesses means the package will, at best, now curb only 0.65% to 1.3% of GHG emissions from a business-as-usual growth pathway by 2030, according to ICCT, where the business as usual pathway is +15% above the industry’s 2008 baseline. This leaves shipping sector emissions around 14% higher in 10 years time than today’s already high level of 1 billion tonnes a year of CO2.. </description>
<dc:date>2021-04-27T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>US-led Summit gives world a fighting chance to meet climate goals</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=2261466</link>
<description> (23 April 2021) A small but important group of world leaders have shown that they grasp the scale of the climate crisis facing us, bringing their A-game to the Leaders Summit on Climate this week.
Manuel Pulgar-Vidal, WWF’s Global Lead Climate &amp; Energy said: “Bold action by a coalition of a few high-ambition countries has given us a fighting chance of keeping global climate goals within reach during this critical decade.”
“The US set the pace with a game-changing target of 50-52% emissions reduction from 2005 levels by 2030, as did the United Kingdom with its target of 78% by 2035. Japan and Canada also presented improved targets. Now, other big emitters such as Australia, and the Russian Federation, and forested countries such as Mexico and Brazil, must step up with equally strong targets. Enhanced 2030 targets by China and India would also be game-changers, he said.
“What is clear is that the end of the fossil fuel era is very much in sight, with enhanced commitments to end international public funding for coal by South Korea, for example and a definite end to fossil fuel subsidies as called for by New Zealand Prime Minister Jacinda Ardern and the US. We urge the G7 and G20 countries to address this issue meaningfully when they meet later this year.”
Many new coalitions were announced or mentioned which have the potential to push sectoral transformation at a speed and scale not yet realized. Key among these are the new LEAF Coalition—Lowering Emissions by Accelerating Forest finance—and the GFANZ Coalition—Glasgow Financial Alliance for Net-Zero—showing a clear trend in the private finance and corporate sectors. They highlight how truly committed companies can go above and beyond their Science Based Targets initiative-validated decarbonization targets to contribute to meaningfully address the intertwined biodiversity and climate crises.
“The ultimate demonstration of the political will of leaders will become more evident in the year ahead, especially around the issue of climate finance. We cannot ignore the urgency to fund adaptation, loss and damage and nature-based solutions. Leaders must ensure their recovery packages and spending are both nature- and climate positive,” said Pulgar-Vidal.
“Overall, I consider this summit’s outcomes to be a hugely important contribution to the global response to the climate crisis, said Pulgar-Vidal.
“It is imperative for the momentum initiated through the Summit to pulse all the way to COP26, so that the outcome there lay a strong foundation for implementation in the years ahead,” he concluded.
Statements by WWF Country Offices
WWF-US Senior Vice President for Climate Change Marcene Mitchell: “During the Leaders&apos; Climate Summit, we heard of innovations in technology, nature-based solutions, and the potential of a clean and equitable energy transition that will spark new life into the economy. But this moment represents just the beginning of a critical year in global climate policy and we have a lot of work ahead of us. We are ready to stand alongside the federal government to tackle the monumental challenge of climate change.&quot;
WWF-China CEO Lu Lunyan: “President Xi has mandated new requirements to intensify coal control and phase down in China, a positive and crucial step to achieve China’s pledges of emission peaking before 2030 and carbon neutrality before 2060. We encourage relevant Chinese authorities to faithfully deliver the new mandate on energy transition, while joining forces with the global community in a robust approach. We also welcome the green initiatives in collaboration with countries along the “Belt &amp; Road.” We encourage China to strengthen cooperation on green, low carbon and renewable energy development.”
WWF European Policy Office Director Ester Asin: &quot;We know that citizens everywhere want climate action, and this summit showed there is government momentum too. However, there is still a huge gap between the emissions reductions needed and what many countries are doing. The EU agreed a climate law committing to climate neutrality by 2050, a 2030 reduction target of -55% net emissions and consistency of its future policies towards those targets. It is an important step, but far from what we need to be in line with science. The EU needs to step up and make sure its upcoming legislation is fit to fight the climate emergency.&quot;
WWF-Latin America Regional Director Roberto Troya: “Addressing the main causes of climate change must be a priority for vulnerable regions like Latin America and the Caribbean. We still have a long way to go to get on the 1.5ºC path. But Colombia and Chile&apos;s announcements during the Leaders Summit on Climate to reduce emissions by 51% by 2030, and to decarbonize energy by 2040, added to the announcement of massive carbon neutrality commitments from the mayors of the Capital Cities of the Americas in the Secretariat of Climate Change (CC35). These are key steps for the region to reach carbon neutrality by 2050. We reinforce the call to Latin America and the Caribbean countries to commit to a just and green transition that leads to environmentally and socially sustainable low-carbon economies.&quot;
---ends---
For more information, contact Mandy Jean Woods mwoods@wwfint.org
</description>
<dc:date>2021-04-23T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Political momentum for climate action cracks open after Climate Leaders Summit today</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=2251966</link>
<description> (22 April 2021) - Today, US President Biden sent a clear message about what he expected from the world leaders attending the virtual Leaders Summit on Climate when he announced a game-changing emissions target for the US.
The U.S. said it would cut emissions by 50-52% by 2030 from 2005 levels, nearly doubling its previous commitment for 2025. This is a historical increase, an unequivocal and very welcome signal of the leading role the US intends to play in climate geopolitics, and a clear motivator for action by fellow big-emitters.
WWF-US Senior Vice President for Climate Change Marcene Mitchell said: “This commitment shows how far we have come as a nation, and it shows what strong and sustained action by cities, sub-national states, communities, businesses, and other institutions can make possible. I hope that this commitment will inspire other big emitters to go further to halve their emissions and make tangible sectoral change by 2030 on a path to full decarbonization by mid-century.” 
Some world leaders responded positively, and it’s clear that many others are getting ready to respond to the scale of the climate crisis we face.
Concrete new announcements include Canada&apos;s new target to decrease emissions by 40-45% from 2005 by 2030, the EU earmarking 1.3 trillion euro for climate goals, including nature-based solutions, Japan announcing a 46% reduction goal by 2030 (compared to 2013) and South Korea commitment to end public finance for overseas coal powered plants and halt permits for any further domestic coal plants. On its part, China said it will control coal-fired power generation projects, as well as strictly limit the increase in coal consumption, in the 2021-2025 period, and phase it down in the 2026-2030 period. South Africa said it will bring forward the plan to peak and plateau emissions in 2025 and decline from 2035 to a decline from 2025.
Other highlights were New Zealand’s compelling call for the elimination of fossil fuels and fossil fuel subsidies, and the African Development Bank being recognized as the first multilateral bank to meet, and exceed, the 50% target of finance for adaptation.
Emerging themes in the leaders&apos; speeches included a potential revamp of debt-for-nature swaps with a focus on adaptation, carbon pricing and green hydrogen production for international markets.
Manuel Pulgar-Vidal, WWF Global Lead Climate and Energy said: “These announcements send the clearest signal yet that the transformation of our various sectors is underway. One of the most evident transformations is in private finance portfolios, which are aligning with climate science. The Glasgow Financial Alliance for Net Zero, announced yesterday, brings existing and new net-zero finance initiatives into one sector-wide strategic forum.
“Countries who read these signals and act immediately, will get ahead of the game. They must start with a strong focus on short-term climate plans aligned with Paris goals, which must be delivered, ahead of COP26”.
A conducive policy environment is essential to enable new private investments to root. Important opportunities for industrialized economies are the upcoming G7 and G20 summits, where structural measures for decarbonization such as the elimination of fossil fuels subsidies, the ramp-up in carbon taxes, and other structural decarbonization measures could be agreed. Big emitting countries must also view strong bilateral and multilateral financial commitments as an essential, complementary piece to their new national commitments, he concluded.
Finance: Many leaders and other speakers recognized the need for increasing finance, and to meet and exceed the $100 billion commitment financing for developing countries from 2020 onwards. But developed countries are not on track to do this, and aside from the US commitment to double their public finance from Obama-era finance, there were no significant new commitments.
Adaptation: Adaptation needs and advances featured strongly in speeches by developing countries, especially the most vulnerable, while developed countries focused on mitigation targets and measures. Many countries highlighted the need for a 50/50 balance in public finance for adaptation and mitigation. Those speeches, however, were unmatched by much-needed financial commitments for adaptation and loss and damage by developed countries. Those remain a key priority for 2021.
Country statements:
WWF-India statement by Dr. T.S. Panwar, Director, Climate Change and Energy Programme: “Echoing the Indian Prime Minister, Mr Narendra Modi’s thoughts, climate action in this decade - at a high speed, on a large scale, and with a global scope is of prime importance as it will shape the future trajectory at the global level. The Indo-US climate and clean energy agenda 2030 partnership announced today, will be helpful in achieving India’s ambitious renewable energy target of 450GW by 2030. One crucial step towards concrete climate action in this decade would be to embrace sustainable lifestyle practices. WWF-India would work towards driving this shift together with various orchestrators in the system.”
Kate Norgrove, Executive Director of Advocacy and Campaigns at WWF UK, said: “As we celebrate Earth Day it is encouraging to see world leaders raise their ambition when it comes to protecting the planet - our one shared home - by strengthening commitments to reduce carbon emissions. This is vital to kick-start momentum. However, with our climate in crisis and nature in free-fall, words need to translate into urgent action. Following the UK’s recent commitment to cut carbon emissions by 78% by 2035, the government must now show global leadership by publishing a comprehensive action plan on how it will reach this new target and net-zero by 2050. This must include introducing a net-zero test for overall government spending to ensure all new investment and policies fully align with the UK’s climate goals.”
Megan Leslie, President and CEO of WWF-Canada said: “Raising Canada’s emissions reduction targets to 45% by 2030 is welcome news, as is the Prime Minister’s acknowledgment of the vital link between protecting nature and fighting climate change. If we’re going to meet these aggressive goals, we can’t talk about climate change without also talking about nature-based climate solutions. Restoring and stewarding ecosystems that capture and hold carbon, and supporting Indigenous-led conservation, are essential to battling our concurrent climate and biodiversity crises.”
New Initiatives statements
WWF International Director General Marco Lambertini said: “Scaling up finance to protect forests and biodiversity is critical to efforts to tackle our connected climate and nature crises. Tropical forests absorb billions of tonnes of carbon each year and host a vast diversity of life forms, while providing multiple other benefits to people locally and globally. The LEAF Coalition is a great example of the kind of innovative and integrated action needed to secure an equitable, net zero, nature-positive future for people and the planet. It is now key to focus on its effective implementation. We need to build on this momentum to set nature on the path to recovery by 2030, in support of climate action. WWF urges government and business leaders to increase financial support and ambitious actions for biodiversity.
For further information, contact Mandy Jean Woods mwoods@wwfint.org </description>
<dc:date>2021-04-22T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>WWF welcomes progress represented by US$1 billion commitment from major new forest and climate coalition</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=2232966</link>
<description> (22 April 2021) - WWF welcomes the groundbreaking US$1 billion coalition that aims to raise global climate ambition and urgently halt deforestation announced today during the Leaders Summit on Climate by the governments of the United States, the United Kingdom and Norway and a group of leading international corporates. Further work ahead is needed to support tropical forest countries and safeguard the rights of forest-dependent communities.
The new LEAF Coalition—Lowering Emissions by Accelerating Forest finance—will enable governments and participating companies to pay for high-quality emissions reductions from tropical forests, which will be verified against an independent standard. According to WWF, these reductions must be in addition to—not a substitute for—deep cuts in these companies’ emissions; guided by a target validated by the Science Based Targets initiative (SBTi); aligned with science and with the goal of achieving net-zero emissions by 2050 or sooner; and able to prevent double counting of emission savings. This must also be accompanied by urgent efforts to secure land rights for Indigenous Peoples and local communities (IPLCs) and action in agricultural supply chains to address deforestation and conversion from commodity production. Governments, forest nations, companies, civil society and, most importantly, IPLCs will have to work together to realize the coalition’s ambitious goals.
Land-use change, including deforestation, is one of the leading causes of climate change and biodiversity loss. WWF realizes that reducing deforestation at scale is a profound challenge for governments and diverse stakeholders in tropical forest countries, requiring north-south, public-private and supply-demand collaborations. We will continue to build these bridges to save the world&apos;s most important forests.
WWF-US President &amp; CEO Carter Roberts said: “With any new climate initiative, the important thing is to deliver high-integrity results at a scale that matters. That means initiatives should be measurable, credible and bring about real emissions reductions. For forest initiatives, they should touch down in places, building deep partnerships with local communities and producing durable benefits for people and nature. And they should also embrace the principle that nature-based solutions to climate change are meant to complement—not replace—emissions cuts. The LEAF Coalition sets the stage to deliver. Its success will depend on honoring these aspects in the design and execution and on building the capacity of countries to do the same.”
Fran Raymond Price, WWF Global Lead, Forests said: “Forests covering an area the size of California, totalling 43 million hectares, were lost in the tropics and sub-tropics in just over a decade, according to WWF’s report Deforestation fronts: Drivers and responses in a changing world. Tackling the drivers of deforestation at scale is a challenge that requires multi-sector partnerships, implementation finance and supply-demand collaborations. Above all, solutions need to recognize the fundamental role of Indigenous Peoples and local communities and the need for sustainable livelihoods. The commitment announced today will help catalyze greater political interest in forest countries to deliver on ambitious targets. It is important to ensure there is shared responsibility in implementing these targets, and solutions are developed alongside Indigenous Peoples and local communities and benefit them.”
Manuel Pulgar-Vidal, WWF Global Lead Climate &amp; Energy said: “This multi-sector, multi-country announcement sends a much-needed signal to tropical forest countries that their efforts to reduce systemic deforestation at jurisdictional and national scales will be rewarded by results-based payments aligned with the Paris Agreement. And it will give companies and investors the opportunity to demonstrate true leadership by going above and beyond their science-based targets validated by SBTi. Companies must hold themselves to the same high standards as the countries offering these credits. WWF looks forward to collaborating with the LEAF Coalition to develop credible strategies that deliver on the global ambition to achieve the 1.5°C goal for the benefit of climate, people and nature.”
WWF International Director General Marco Lambertini said: “Scaling up finance to protect forests and biodiversity is critical to efforts to tackle our connected climate and nature crises. Tropical forests absorb billions of tonnes of carbon each year and host a vast diversity of life forms, while providing multiple other benefits to people locally and globally. The LEAF Coalition is a great example of the kind of innovative and integrated action needed to secure an equitable, net zero, nature-positive future for people and the planet. It is now key to focus on its effective implementation. We need to build on this momentum to set nature on the path to recovery by 2030, in support of climate action. WWF urges government and business leaders to increase financial support and ambitious actions for biodiversity.
Notes to Editors:
LEAF Coalition website: www.leafcoalition.org
Science Based Targets initiative website: https://sciencebasedtargets.org/
WWF urges countries to endorse the Leaders’ Pledge for Nature, committing to reversing biodiversity loss this decade.
WWF has experts available for interviews on the issues mentioned above. Contact
Huma Khan, WWF Global Communications Manager, Forest Practice huma.khan@wwfint.org
Mandy Jean Woods, WWF Global Communications Manager, Climate &amp; Energy mwoods@wwfint.org 
</description>
<dc:date>2021-04-22T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Biden’s Summit marks kick off to crunch year for climate action</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=2099966</link>
<description> (16 April 2021) - The Leaders’ Summit on Climate, a meeting being hosted by US President Biden, kicks off both the ‘decade of delivery’ for climate, nature and development and a crunch year for climate action. The two-day meeting starts on Earth Day, 22 April.
Many leaders from the world’s biggest economies and from some of the world’s most vulnerable countries, will convene virtually to discuss how to unlock the transformative change required to tackle the climate crisis.
The expected announcement by the US of its revised climate emission targets and the anticipated announcements by leaders attending, is a chance for the Summit to accelerate the political momentum needed to ensure a successful outcome at COP26, so lay the foundations for effective delivery in the years to come.
Manuel Pulgar-Vidal, WWF Global Lead Climate &amp; Energy said: “The overriding quest by leaders attending this summit must be to catalyse efforts that keep the 1.5°C goal within reach. They must announce tangible actions that accelerate the transformational change needed to halve global emissions by 2030.
“We won’t meet this goal if we don’t unlock the political will needed to ensure a successful outcome at COP26, and put the elements on the table - like climate finance - necessary to implement plans. We are waiting anxiously for the world’s richest countries - including the United States - to lead by example with the greatest ambition, putting promises into action,” he said.
Pulgar-Vidal said the commitments made by cities, business and other sub-national organizations must also be reflected in national climate plans, which need to be backed-up with conducive policy environments. “Very specifically, leaders must include concrete policies and actions to scale up nature-based solutions and phase out harmful subsidies, starting with eliminating all fossil fuel subsidies.”
He further encouraged leaders to sign up to the Leaders Pledge for Nature, and to speed up the implementation of those commitments.
The overarching focus of the summit is increasing climate ambition. This is most evident in the national climate plans (or Nationally Determined Contributions, NDCs) which countries are required to submit to the UN as part of their Paris Agreement commitments and in long-term strategies. Cutting through these are critical issues of adaptation and resilience and climate finance.
WWF believes the following are crucial to these:
A strong whole-of-society approach: Push to ground all long-term strategy net zero commitments and ambitious NDCs in immediate, transformative decarbonization actions across sectors of the economy. While it should be no substitute for national action, leaders’ statements should embrace the critical role that businesses, cities, states, other sub-national institutions will play in implementation and their commitment to back-up their progressive action with conducive national policy. 
Bring greater emphasis and action to nature-based solutions: Encourage country commitments to be inclusive of quality nature-based solutions as part of their plan to both reduce emissions and build resilience. This should include: 
Additional support of the Leaders Pledge for Nature, as well as a commitment to nature to 30% of international climate finance and an overall increase in climate finance.
A commitment to end deforestation and habitat conversion.
Ecosystem-based adaptation opportunities in all countries.Economic stimulus and recovery packages that are climate and nature-positive.
Scale up public and private finance: Increase and encourage core finance commitments to bring the support needed to the Green Climate Fund, the Global Environment Facility, and other such public finance mechanisms while harnessing the power of private finance to mobilize investors, including through TCFD and TNFD. This should also include a firm commitment to eliminate harmful subsidies, beginning with a firm deadline to end fossil fuel subsidies by G20 later this year.
Notes to Editors:
Find out more about WWF’s recommendations for how the Biden administration should act on climate going into the summit here. Additional WWF materials related to the Leaders’ Summit on Climate here (statements, op-eds, events).
WWF is hosting the following key events during the US Climate Action Week: 
The Political Legacy of 2021: Reflections from Past COP Presidents &amp; Climate Leaders.Join Manuel Pulgar-Vidal, (WWF Global Lead Climate &amp; Energy and COP20 President) and his guests Laurent Fabius (COP21 President, President of the Constitutional Council of France); Carolina Schmidt (COP25 President, Chilean Minister of Environment), Dr Jonathan Pershing (Senior Advisor to US Presidential Envoy on Climate) and Helen Mountford (Vice President, Climate &amp; Economics, WRI) in a conversation about possible elements for the legacy of the 2021 momentum to multilateralism, with a focus on COP26. It takes place on Tuesday 20 April at 8am EDT. Register here to join.
Scaling Business Action for Climate and Nature: A CEO Dialogue
Join WWF-US CEO Carter Roberts and corporate leaders for a dialogue about making corporate climate leadership a reality on Wednesday 21 April at 3 pm ET.
Register here to join.
All In For Climate: How a Whole-of-Society Approach Can Accelerate the Race to Zero Join Alliances for Climate Action and the UNFCCC Race to Zero Campaign for a conversation with leading subnational and non-state actors to discuss the opportunities that a “whole-of-society” approach to the climate crisis offers. It takes place on Wednesday 21 April at 8 am ET. Register here to join.
Our Planet: Too Big To Fail
Join WWF and the British Embassy for a virtual screening of the film: Our Planet: Too Big To Fail. The fill will be followed by a panel discussion with some cast members and special guests on how we can transform the global financial system to deliver a sustainable, net-zero future. It takes place on Wednesday, April 21 at 9am ET. Register here to join.
Our experts are available for interviews/comments/analysis before, during and after the Summit:
Spokespersons
Topic/Theme
Contact
WWF International
Manuel Pulgar-Vidal
WWF Global Lead,
Climate &amp; Energy
Climate narrative
Global expectations for the Summit
Implications for COP26
Political assessment
Mandy Jean Woods
mwoods@wwfint.org
+49 1511 885 4162
Karen Richards
krichards@wwfint.org
+44 775 552 59
Vanessa Perez-Cirera
WWF Deputy Global Lead,
Climate &amp; Energy
Climate narrative
International policy
Nature-based solutions
Sectoral transformation
Margaret Kuhlow
WWF Global Lead, Finance
Climate finance
Public, private sector, multilateral financing
Key initiatives in the finance sector contributing to climate action momentum (like TCFD, TNFD)
WWF-US
Carter Roberts
WWF-US CEO
WWF-US Key priorities, initiatives
US policy
Private sector engagement
Evan Carlson
evan.carlson@wwfus.org
+1 202 495-4756
Marcene Mitchell
WWF-US SVP for Climate Change
WWF-US climate change initiatives
US Policy
Mariana Panuncio-Feldman
WWF US Senior Director, Climate Policy Action
Alliances for Climate Action
America Is All In
Role of non-state actors in galvanizing climate action
Genevieve Maricle
WWF US Director, US Climate Policy Action
America Is All
US Policy
</description>
<dc:date>2021-04-16T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>“A champion for the environment”</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=1996416</link>
<description> </description>
<dc:date>2021-04-09T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nearly 40 sharks and rays reclassified as threatened, including one species of ray already possibly extinct</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=1834916</link>
<description> “The alarm-bells for sharks and rays could not be ringing louder,” said Dr. Andy Cornish, Leader of Sharks: Restoring the Balance, WWF’s global shark and ray conservation programme. “The sheer number and diversity of these animals facing extinction is staggering. Overfishing is by far the greatest threat and has to be reined in. The good news is that solutions to this crisis do exist. Governments and the regional fisheries management organisations, which manage fishing in the high seas, must act now and boldly to recover the most threatened species before it is too late.”
Most alarmingly, IUCN reveals that one species of ray may have already gone extinct, as the Java stingaree (Urolophus javanicus) is now assessed as Critically Endangered (Possibly Extinct). A unique ray from the coast of Java in Indonesia, it was previously listed as Critically Endangered (2006). This endemic species has not been seen since the end of the 19th century when it was originally discovered.
Eight out of nine species that are “uplisted” to the Critically Endangered category – meaning they are just one step away from extinction – are rays (mostly guitarfishes and eagle rays). This continues the worrying trend that although rays may be less known and do not receive as much attention, they are doing even worse than sharks as a consequence of overfishing and overall lack of fisheries management.
Nonetheless, it is not just the lesser-known species featuring in this round of Red List updates. A few reef sharks that used to be very common and abundant, and are particularly popular among divers, are now threatened. This includes the Caribbean reef shark (Carcharhinus perezi) reclassified from Near Threatened to Endangered, lemon shark (Negaprion brevirostris) from Near Threatened to Vulnerable, and the Atlantic nurse shark (Ginglymostoma cirratum) from Data Deficient to Vulnerable.
“The latest reassessments highlight that fishing is causing population declines across the spectrum of these ancient animals,” Dr. Cornish commented. “Whether rays or sharks, those on sunlit coral reefs, far offshore, or in the deep oceans, large and small – few groups are unscathed.”
Ever more species of sharks and rays are being pushed towards extinction. In 2014, 25% of all shark and ray species were threatened, with 25 species critically endangered. Right now, 36% per cent is under threat and the number of critically endangered species has tripled (from 25 to 76).
More than 1,200 different species of sharks and rays inhabit our global ocean. These diverse animals do not simply dwell there – they shape the ocean, and have done so for more than 400 million years, since the time of dinosaurs. Sharks and rays are indispensable to ocean health and the well-being of millions of people across the globe through provision of livelihoods, food, and tourism.
-END-
NOTES TO EDITORS:
76 shark and ray species are now critically endangered, 112 are endangered, and 167 are vulnerable.
Sharks: Restoring the Balance is a joint global programme of WWF and TRAFFIC focusing on shark and ray conservation. Founded in 2014, the programme supports conservation teams working in over 20 countries and territories across 6 continents and focuses on fisheries management, trade, and consumption. Visit sharks.panda.org to learn more.
WWF is an independent conservation organization, with over 30 million followers and a global network active in nearly 100 countries. Our mission is to stop the degradation of the planet&apos;s natural environment and to build a future in which people live in harmony with nature, by conserving the world&apos;s biological diversity, ensuring that the use of renewable natural resources is sustainable, and promoting the reduction of pollution and wasteful consumption. Visit panda.org/news for the latest news and media resources; follow us on Twitter @WWF_media
PRESS CONTACT:
Magda Nieduzak
Senior Communications Officer
WWF Sharks: Restoring the Balance
mnieduzak@wwf.org.hk
</description>
<dc:date>2021-03-25T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>2021 must see a strongly backed climate adaptation agenda that parallels deep decarbonization action</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=1282966</link>
<description> 
20 January 2021 - While the world needs to rapidly ramp up efforts to cut emissions, countries also need to urgently accelerate efforts to adapt to the increasingly severe impacts of climate change. This is the key focus of the first global Climate Adaptation Summit, being held on 25 -26 January, highlighting the urgency for countries to develop effective climate adaptation plans.
Adaptation – reducing countries’, communities’ and ecosystems&apos; vulnerability to the climate crisis by increasing their resilience – is a key pillar of the Paris Agreement on Climate Change. The agreement requires countries to implement adaptation measures as part of their enhanced Nationally Determined Contributions (NDCs) outlined through National Adaptation Plans (NAPs). For example, NAPs could include climate information systems, early warning, measures to reduce disaster or drought risk, investments in a green future, among other things. These are some elements necessary for robust adaptation strategies, underscoring the urgent need for immediate investment in ambitious initiatives to build resilience to the increasingly destructive impacts of the climate crisis.
The virtual Summit will convene global leaders such former UN Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon and current UN Secretary General Antonio Guterres, UK Prime Minister Boris Johnson; French President Emmanuel Macron, German Chancellor Angela Merkel and many others to discuss adaptation issues. The Summit will launch an ‘action-propelling’ global Adaptation Action Agenda, aiming to accelerate climate adaptation action over the next decade.
Manuel Pulgar-Vidal, WWF global lead for climate and energy, said: “This meeting is timeous, necessary and the urgency has never been greater. Sadly, as we start to witness the increasingly severe impacts of climate change, countries also have to accelerate efforts to adapt as well as mitigate.
“The most vulnerable communities all over the world are feeling the impacts of the climate crisis, and ecosystems that they depend upon are under pressure from extreme floods, droughts, wildfires and rising seas, and these impacts are only going to get worse.”
Sandeep Chamling Rai, WWF senior advisor for global adaptation policy, said: “This year, we need to see global urgency and ambition in adaptation and building climate resilience. The Summit must pave the way for the journey ahead.”
Vanessa Perez-Cirera, WWF deputy global lead for climate and energy, said: “Climate adaptation is not only about technology and infrastructure, but also about the role nature can play in building climate adaptation and resilience. The potential of Nature-based Solutions for climate change - one of the most integral and cost-effective adaptation tools - has yet to be unleashed. Nature can help countries be more resilient to climate change - but if we don&apos;t protect it and help it adapt, it can&apos;t help us in turn.”
Investing in sustainable adaptation solutions can help the world to tackle twin global crises: climate change and nature loss. WWF is working across the globe to build more climate resilient societies and ecosystems, including through Nature-based Solutions and innovative financial solutions. For example, WWF and partners are collaborating on the ambitious Resilient Asian Deltas initiative to help stop the deltas from sinking and shrinking and keep them above the rising seas. WWF is also co-managing the game-changing Dutch Fund for Climate and Development, which uses public funds to leverage new private finance into bankable projects that build climate resilience.
Stuart Orr, WWF global lead for freshwater said: “Rapidly increasing investment in healthy rivers, lakes and wetlands will be critical to global efforts to adapt to climate change since its impacts will most immediately and acutely be felt through water.
“Public funds will never fill the adaptation gap. Innovative financial approaches – such as WWF’s Bankable Nature Solutions – can help channel billions in new private investment into sustainable bankable projects that enhance the health of freshwater ecosystems, which will boost adaptation, water security and freshwater biodiversity&quot;.
WWF works with a variety of partners to:
Elevate the role of Nature-based Solutions for climate adaptation and the need for increased public and blended finance to reach the most vulnerable communities;
Work with the International Union for Conservation of Nature to develop and pilot standards for Nature-based Solutions;
Provide practical guidance for countries to include Nature-based Solutions in their national climate plans (or Nationally Determined Contributions - NDCs);
Propose ways to align concepts, measures and safeguards between the United Nations Framework for Climate Change and the Post-2020 Framework for the Convention on Biological Diversity;
Develop science-based guidance for synergistic interventions;
Identify policy, governance and financial solutions to sustainably fund and scale projects;
Work with local communities and indigenous groups to design and develop best in class projects that benefit climate, nature and people.
Channel investment into climate-smart agriculture, forest and wetland restoration, resilient coral reefs to help communities adapt to climate change.
​Notes for Editors
A recent report by the UN Environmental Programme noted that 72% of countries have adopted at least one national-level adaptation planning instrument, while a further 9% are developing one. Most developing countries are preparing National Adaptation Plans and including adaptation actions in their updated NDCs. But finance for these plans falls far short of what is needed to ensure implementation.
Join these WWF events at the Summit - remember you have to register to get access to the events.
Launch of the Race to Resilience campaign by UN Climate Change and the Climate Champions at 4pm CET, right after the opening event. This is a partner campaign with the Race to Zero.
The Resilient Asian Deltas initiative will be featured in the Water Action Track. WWF co-hosted an event in Viet Nam with the governments of Viet Nam and the Netherlands, World Bank and Delta Alliance and that recording will also be featured during the Summit.
The Dutch Fund for Climate and Development (co-managed by WWF Green Finance Unit) will showcase how public funds can leverage huge amounts of new private finance into Bankable Nature Solutions to build resilient societies, economies and ecosystems. 
Launch of joint WWF &amp; Dutch government report on Water as Leverage as part of a side session in the Water Action Track on the importance of water and freshwater ecosystems to effective climate adaptation. The event involves Dutch government, WWF’s Stuart Orr (FW Practice Lead), World Bank, OECD, Valuing Water Initiative and Water Youth Network.
For further information, contact
Mandy Jean Woods mwoods@wwfint.org or Richard Lee rlee@wwfint.org
</description>
<dc:date>2021-01-22T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>World must not lose sight of urgency, resources necessary for most impacted countries to adapt to climate change</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=1245441</link>
<description> 14 January 2021 – While the world’s attention is necessarily focused on the COVID-19 pandemic, it is imperative to not lose sight of the need to step up adaptation action now. Failure to do so could have catastrophic economic and societal impacts, according to a new UN report published today.
Reflecting on the UN Environment Programme’s Adaptation Gap 2020 report, WWF senior advisor for global adaptation policy Sandeep Chamling Rai said, “The climate impacts that we are experiencing now are just the tip of the iceberg. These impacts are only going to get worse over time. It is vital that countries move to faster implementation of their National Adaptation action Plans, and that globally, there is greater investment to support building climate resilience.”
Adaptation – reducing countries’ and communities’ vulnerability to climate change by increasing their ability to adapt to impacts – is a key pillar of the Paris Agreement on Climate Change. The agreement requires its signatories to implement adaptation measures through national plans, climate information systems, early warning, protective measures and investments in a green future.
Key findings from the report show that almost three-quarters of nations have some adaptation plans in place, but financing and implementation fall far short of what is needed; financing for adaptation is only 5% of tracked climate funds (around US$30 billion per year); and Nature-based Solutions is critical for adaptation and needs to receive more attention.
Nature-based Solutions provide human well-being and biodiversity benefits by protecting, sustainably managing and restoring natural or modified ecosystems.
Chamling Rai said, “In the adaptation context, Nature-based Solutions are a low-cost option that reduces climate risks, restores and protects biodiversity and brings benefits for communities and economies. It is a triple win for people, planet and nature.”
UNEP Executive Director Inger Andersen said, “As the UN Secretary-General has said, we need a global commitment to put half of all global climate finance towards adaptation in the next year. This will allow a huge step up in adaptation – in everything from early warning systems to resilient water resources to nature-based solutions.”
Chamling Rai said: “2021 must be the year for scaling up adaptation efforts and uniting together for global ambition on adaptation implementation. Rich countries have a moral responsibility to ensure there are sufficient resources allocated to poor countries to implement adaptation plans. Poor countries are, after all, least responsible for climate change, but are most at risk.”
WWF is working across the globe to build more climate resilient societies and ecosystems, including through Nature-based Solutions and innovative financial solutions. For example, WWF and partners are collaborating on the ambitious Resilient Asian Deltas initiative to help stop the deltas from sinking and shrinking and keep them above the rising seas. WWF is also co-managing the game-changing Dutch Fund for Climate and Development, which uses public funds to leverage new private finance into bankable projects that build climate resilience.
Notes for Editors:
Useful facts from the UNEP Adaptation Gap 2020 report:
Adaptation planning is growing, but funding and implementation is lagging.
72% of countries have adopted at least one national-level adaptation planning instrument.
Most developing countries are preparing National Adaptation Plans (NAPs).
Since 2006, close to 400 adaptation projects financed by multilateral funds serving the Paris Agreement have taken place in developing countries. But of over 1,700 adaptation initiatives surveyed, only 3% had already reported real reductions to climate risks posed to the communities where the projects were being implemented.
The Green Climate Fund has allocated 40% of its total portfolio to adaptation and is increasingly crowding-in private sector investment.
An analysis of four major climate and development funds (Global Environment Facility, Green Climate Fund, Adaptation Fund and International Climate Initiative) show that only US$ 12 billion was spent on Nature-based Solutions, while cumulative investment for climate change mitigation and adaptation projects under the four funds stood at USD 94 billion.
For further information, contact Mandy Jean Woods mwoods@wwfint.org </description>
<dc:date>2021-01-14T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mauritius oil spill: priorities and recommendations</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=646271</link>
<description> Local and international response
WWF praises the local organizations and community groups on Mauritius for their rapid response to the oil spill and for their efforts to remove oil. WWF welcomes the news that the international community is mobilizing to support Mauritius in its clean-up efforts.
Concerns and immediate priorities
The front portion of the ship has been moved and sunk. WWF believes a better option would have been to take the floating and secured damaged portion to a safe refuge where disposal options could be assessed. WWF hopes that the operation regarding the remainder of the MV Wakashio will follow such established practice, so the vessel can be dismantled and disposed of in a way that does not pose a threat to local ecosystems.
WWF remains deeply concerned by the amount of oil that leaked from the MV Wakashio and into the coastal waters of Mauritius, where it is coating beaches, coral reefs, seagrasses and mangroves in a poisonous sludge and putting lagoon fisheries as well as whales, dolphins, seabirds and sea turtles at risk of toxic contamination.
There is also significant risk of potential long-term damage associated with sediment burial of oil, and then chronic impacts as the oil and other contaminants affect the food chain over the longer term. The shedding of potentially toxic anti-fouling coatings is also of concern, along with the physical damage to the reef from the grounding.
The priority now must be on removing as much of the oil as possible from the coastal system, managing the direct and indirect effects of the oil on wildlife and habitats, and assessing and responding to the impact of the spill on the communities and economic sectors. 
Natural resource damage assessment and restoration, and international support
We need “all hands on deck’’ to support Mauritius in this crisis. We need environmental scientists and biological experts to quickly set up monitoring programmes to track the impact of the spill, including the potential contamination of fisheries and coastal sediments and habitats.
WWF calls for a natural resource damage assessment (NRDA) to determine the significance of impacts caused by this oil spill. The NRDA should include inputs from affected communities and the public, and experts should determine the extent of damage as well as best methods for restoration activities. The types of impacts that should be assessed include habitats and ecosystems, with special attention to species of importance for livelihoods or nutrition, and socio-economic impacts, including to the asset base on which the tourism industry depends. The NRDA should look at direct, indirect, and cumulative impacts. The establishment of a comprehensive monitoring programme is a top priority.
Shipping and oil spill response
The global community needs to mobilize to drive shipping reform and oil spill preparedness to prevent such spills from happening again. Vulnerable Small Island Developing States cannot be left to bear the burden of lost ocean productivity, clean-up and restoration on their own.
The regional oil spill contingency mechanism, led by the Indian Ocean Commission, and other relevant country groupings such as the Nairobi Convention, should draw lessons and implement policy solutions to prevent such occurrences, and hold those responsible to account if incidents do occur.
Of course, prevention is better than cure. WWF recommends routing measures to keep ships well away from sensitive areas, and ensuring mariners are aware of this via electronic charts and mapping.
Support to those affected
Support should be provided to the people most affected by the oil spill, in particular the fishing communities and those dependent on lagoon resources for nutrition and livelihoods. This includes support and advice on accessing compensation mechanisms, especially if they use an on-line format.
Oil spills are fully avoidable; when they occur, those responsible must be held accountable and funds for the clean-up must be released quickly. Too often, the process of securing compensation and payment takes years to be completed. We call on the company and the flag state to move quickly and release funds for the clean-up effort, when they can be put to immediate use. A comprehensive, independent investigation and inquiry should be launched with a commitment to making the findings public. However, securing funds for the clean-up should not wait until the findings of an inquiry.
Any compensation should also cover the implementation of a longer-term restoration plan for damaged natural resources, which may take years. These natural resources are the foundation for the food and livelihoods of coastal communities, as well as the basis for the country’s tourism industry.
Blue economy and wildlife
Coastal tourism, fishing, seafood processing and seaport activities contribute over 10.5% of the Mauritian GDP, with total direct employment estimated at over 7,000, excluding coastal tourism.
The task of managing the rehabilitation and ultimate restoration of the affected habitats must be scaled up and resourced adequately to put Mauritius on the road to recovery, underpinned by a sustainable ocean-based economy.
Protecting populations of great whales is an important strategy for building a “blue economy.” Globally, whale and dolphin watching is valued at over US$2 billion annually. Healthy populations of whales and coastal dolphins are crucial for sustainably managed tourism in Mauritius.
Globally, whales and dolphins rely on specific ocean habitats – areas where they feed, mate, give birth, or migrate – for their survival. Mauritius is a hub for a variety of iconic species. Humpback whales also make their epic migrations north from their summer feeding grounds off Antarctica to breed in the Southwest Indian Ocean. </description>
<dc:date>2020-08-27T08:10:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>The challenges and opportunities of inclusive conservation in Salonga</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=359690</link>
<description> Within the Democratic Republic of the Congo, in an area so remote that it can only be accessed by water or air, lies the Salonga National Park.
Extending over 33,350km2, Africa’s largest forest national park is home to local and indigenous communities who share their home with 51 known species of mammals, 129 species of fish, and 223 species of birds, including forest elephants, bonobos, bongos, giant pangolins, and the endemic Congo peacock.
Historical challenges and rising pressures
Unfortunately, Salonga has faced many years of turmoil as a result of civil conflict. This has resulted in significant instability. People living in the region face terrible socio-economic hardship, with weak governance and a lack of services.
Salonga was classified as a World Heritage site in 1984. But its incredible biodiversity is under intense threat today from poaching and wildlife trafficking, which endanger its heritage status and, critically, the lives and livelihoods of the people who depend on its resources.The area has recently suffered from significant wildlife crime as poachers have targeted elephants for ivory. There is also a large commercial trade in bushmeat from the area to markets in Congolese cities.
Pressure on the government ecoguards tasked with protecting Salonga against such threats are an all too real challenge. And while their jobs are difficult and dangerous, violence by some government ecoguards against community members is an equally grave concern. There have been disturbing reports in recent years of some government ecoguards using inappropriate force against local community members.To assist efforts to hold accountable government rangers accused of criminal acts, WWF Internationalcommissioned a report from a local human rights groupfor the express purpose of assisting the government in holding any violent rangers to account. The investigative team reviewed substantial evidence relating to 21 allegations against rangers and/or military personnel and interviewed reported victims, witnesses, and accused. With even a single case of violation being one too many, especially for people that have been historically marginalized and discriminated against in the DRC, the findings of the recent report are distressing. WWF has and will continue to advocate for and fully support swift prosecution of any government ecoguard involved in any violence against community members.
Inclusive conservation
WWF’s goal is to protect both people and nature in Salonga, towards our vision of a future in which both people and nature thrive.
As WWF and other conservation organisations make the call for an ambitiousNew Deal for Nature and People, including scientific targets that reverse nature loss, address the climate crisis, and deliver on the Sustainable Development Goals, we continue to advance strengthened approaches to conservation that support Indigenous Peoples and local communities to secure rights and access to their collective lands and territories.
To date in Salonga, we’ve played a key role in the following actions:
Creation and official validation of 172.807 ha community forests, providing land rights to local communities achieved 3 community forests (13.000 ha) by indigenous BaTwa and further 250.000 ha of community forests in the park corridor in process of creation and validation.
350 CLD (comités locaux de développement - local development committees) as well as 5 CARG (Conseil Agricole Rural de Gestion - Rural Agricultural Management Council), 3 CLER (Comité Local d’Entretien Routier - Local Road Maintenance Committee) and 171 Organisations paysannes (Farmer associations) set up. Working on rural development activities with partner organizations. A key focus of these interventions has been on conservation agriculture—measures to intensify farming as an alternative to slash and burn cropping, mainly by supporting farmer field schools and pilot farms, facilitating market access, supporting extension and setting up seed banks and nurseries.
Supporting the development of two community health centers for the BaTwa, supported cottage industries (i.e. soap making) and invested in literacy education for the BaTwa people.
Our continued engagement with the government in Salonga National Park is conditioned on a mutual agreement to operationalize protections for human rights, including demonstrated commitment to systemic changes to ensure that human rights are given the highest priority.
While these discussions proceed, we are already engaged with the Government to identify and mitigate risks for communities related to conservation activities in Salonga, and in addition we are:
As part of WWF’s enhanced Environmental and Social Safeguards Framework, working with the government’s l’Institut Congolais pour la Conservation de la Nature (ICCN) to identify actions to reduce risks, including a mandatory guide of conduct to be signed by all government ecoguards, offering training and mentoring on human rights and calling for immediate consequences for any misconduct according to regulations in place in the DRC;
Taking steps to ensure all government ecoguards in Salonga undergo further training in human rights prior to being permitted to join patrols from Jan 2020 onwards; and
Urgently advancing a new and strengthened grievance mechanism to be available to all community members in and around the park, to be run by an independent human rights organization.
With a recent biomonitoring assessment confirming relatively stable populations of elephants and bonobos -1,600 forest elephants and 15,000 bonobos – it is critical to ensure conservation also delivers positive impact for the people in Salonga who depend on its biodiversity the most. This is why we are looking to further improve our understanding of the local economy and market chains, promote and support GESI (Gender and Social Inclusivity) programming, and help adapt the landscape governance model to ensure local communities have a larger voice and role in its management. It is not an easy feat, but it is one we are wholly committed to and will remain so.
As we work to help secure the long-term future of Salonga for the well-being of people and nature, both locally and worldwide, we remain fully committed to work together with partners and local communities to protect Salonga and the people who depend on it.
</description>
<dc:date>2020-02-11T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Statement on WWF efforts in Messok Dja</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=359531</link>
<description> At WWF, we know that people and nature go hand in hand and local and indigenous communities must be a cornerstone of conservation efforts. It is the guiding principle that we hold ourselves to, and one that we are committed to continually review our work against, especially in the world’s most complex, fragile places where people and nature are both at risk, such as the Messok Dja landscape in the Republic of Congo.
We are therefore deeply concerned with the findings of a draft report of the UN Development Programme (UNDP) Social and Environmental Compliance Unit (SECU)due to be published for public consultation. As we aim to create positive impact for people and nature, the report highlights the underlying issues and challenges facing communities and organizations like ours on the ground that we have been working hard to address. We are especially distressed by the concerns raised regarding relationships between government-employed rangers and local communities, including allegations of abuse, and we are treating these as matters of highest importance. Any breach of our social and human rights commitments is unacceptable to us.
As we take a close look at the report’s observations and analyse fully how the steps we have been putting in place can help further address the issues raised, it is important to note that some of the observations are limited to a field visit in February 2019 before reforms currently underway were in place, and the present draft contains various factual inaccuracies related to WWF’s role and involvement in the government-led ETIC programme. We will continue to do all we can to address the deeper concerns raised, and tackle the challenges communities and civil society organizations like ours are confronted with in fragile, high-risk areas.
As the Republic of Congo considers possibilities to protect the Messok Dja forests from escalating pressures, we have been working very hard towards ensuring local communities and their voices are heard. In November 2019, on the basis of expert analyses we commissioned, we helped bring together representatives of 35 of the 37 concerned communities around Messok Dja, the two impacted logging companies, the government (delegation of Indigenous Peoples, delegation of Protected Areas, delegation of Forest Economy), CSOs together with the NGO consortium of Brainforest, Comptoir Juridique Junior and Cercle des Populations Autochtones de la Sangha, accompanied by a fourth NGO (FGDH) acting as an independent observer,to identify a way forwardfor Messok Dja, with communities and for communities.
Local people and communities must be stewards of conservation efforts. This is why we have been reviewing our approach in Messok Dja for the past 18 months, sharing updates here and here, to identify solutions together with the communities, and we will continue to do so, learning from and together with partners like UNDP.
***
Additional background:
We have officially written to UNDP to clarify the following inaccuraices in the current draft version of the SECU report:
-Information on allegations:We are concerned that in the draft version of the report, SECU has not so far shared information that will enable the RoC authorities or ETIC to take further action on the allegations it raises. We have requested the SECU team to share its findings with us so we can act together to refer these to the competent authorities immediately and also take action against any WWF staff found to be in breach of our policies, processes and commitments.
-The situation on the ground today:The report is based on observations from a field mission conducted almost a year ago and does not reflect the critical steps taken since in terms of grievance mechanisms, regular weekly meetings being held in villages to raise concerns, the progress made on collective stakeholder meetings and dialogue to discuss forest governance etc.
-Current community access to Messok Dja:Messok Dja is currently part of two logging concessions and does not have a specific protected status. There is therefore no restriction of access for communities living in and around the forests and we are deeply concerned by the report’s assertions on restrictions on community access.
-WWF’s role in the ETIC programme:ETIC is an entity which is distinct to WWF. While it is a collaboration between the government of the Republic of Congo and WWF, ETIC staff are formal employees of the state, their employment contract is signed by the Ministry MEFDDE (known as MEF now) and this includes government ecoguards. The staff working for WWF in the ETIC programme, namely the technical coordinator and staff, work on the basis of full time consultancy contracts with WWF. Also, while the total budget of the UNDP programme was at USD 23,807 million, the specific grant to WWF was for an amount of USD194,000. </description>
<dc:date>2020-02-07T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>New WWF study challenges asset managers to respond to call for greater leadership in responsible investment</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=358951</link>
<description> SINGAPORE, January 30, 2020 – Launched today, WWF’s new study and online tool – RESPOND (Resilient and Sustainable Portfolios that Protect Nature and Drive Decarbonisation) – provides asset managers with a means to move beyond current market practices to improve portfolio resilience and alignment with a low carbon and sustainable future, through science-based approaches to responsible investment (RI).
The findings of the study, which analyses the publicly disclosed responsible investment approaches of 22 ESG-leader[1] asset managers operating in Asia, show that important first steps have been taken to address climate-related risks. However, asset managers now need to complement their RI approaches by also focusing on other threats from natural capital loss, including water risk, deforestation, biodiversity loss and ocean degradation, and by making greater reference to science-based criteria when addressing sustainability issues in their investment portfolios. Such action will be crucial for achieving the Paris Agreement and Sustainable Development Goals, as humanity edges closer to key tipping points in Earth’s natural systems and the risks that the climate emergency and natural capital degradation pose to financial stability become ever clearer.
Asia at greater risk 
Asia is particularly at risk, with many of the region’s economies founded on industries like manufacturing, fisheries and agriculture. All of these depend on healthily functioning natural capital and are highly exposed to climate change. The ADB has warned that unabated warming could undermine the significant socio-economic development the region has achieved, and has emphasized that climate change could have “severe effects on livelihoods which in turn would affect human health, migration dynamics and the potential for conflicts.” For asset managers, greater consideration of climate and natural capital risks when investing, and engaging with unsustainable businesses in Asia, will be key to ensuring more resilient and sustainable Asian investment portfolios.
“The continued loss of our biodiversity and natural capital, alongside the crisis of climate change, severely threatens our collective survival. By supporting portfolio companies with time-bound and science-based expectations to address natural capital issues and by engaging them as shareholders, asset managers can help transform Asia’s economies into ones that ensure socioeconomic wellbeing while protecting and restoring natural capital. In doing so, they can demonstrate to asset owners their ability to improve long-term sustainability and portfolio resilience.” said Jeanne Stampe, WWF’s Head of Asia Sustainable Finance.
Based on WWF’s best practice responsible investment framework, the RESPOND online tool showcases how 22 asset managers approach responsible investment across six pillars: purpose, policies, processes, people, products, and portfolio. RESPOND empowers asset managers to enhance their responsible investment capabilities, encouraging a race to the top in the industry.
The tool will be of particular interest to asset owners, who can use its insights to engage asset managers. Keiichi Nakajima, General Manager of MS&amp;AD Insurance Group, said, “WWF’s RESPOND tool and framework offer useful reference points for comparing asset managers on their approaches to responsible investment and climate change. We believe RESPOND will help us to engage with asset managers, and that asset managers will use it to identify areas for improvement. We expect all the asset managers in the region will play key roles in sustainable finance by adapting best practices through RESPOND.”
Key findings
The findings show that the 22 asset managers currently deploy a wide array of approaches to integrate sustainability, and in particular climate change, into their investment processes. As shown in the summary graph (see figure in Annex), the 22 asset managers’ overall strong performance on the ‘Purpose’, ‘Process’ and ‘Products’ pillars of WWF’s responsible investment framework reflects how efforts so far to integrate climate change and sustainability into their businesses have focused on commitments, procedural innovation, and product development. In this way, they set the pace among asset managers competing for mandates from asset owners with increasingly ambitious climate strategies.
However, to cement their status as industry leaders, they will need to complement their progress to date with additional efforts on the ‘Policies’, ‘People’, and ‘Portfolio’ pillars. Addressing sub-indicators under ‘Policies’ in particular will be critical to ensure their efforts and commitments translate into real change in their investee companies. Here is where they can leverage their leadership and push the boundaries of responsible investment, especially in Asia, even further – on climate change, but also on wider issues like accelerating nature loss and ecosystem collapse. For example, of the 22 asset managers in the study:
100% publicly recognize the long-term risks that climate change poses and support the TCFD recommendations, but just 36% have or will set targets to align their portfolios with a 1.5°C climate target.
90% consider water risk as a part of their investment decision making processes, but only 18% expect companies to practice water stewardship.
82% consider issues like deforestation and biodiversity loss when making investment decisions, but only 36% expect investee companies to obtain or support relevant sustainability standards that safeguard against these risks.
Just 14% state that ocean sustainability is incorporated into investment decision-making, and none expect investee companies to obtain or support relevant sustainability standards to safeguard against these risks
Based on the above and other key findings, it is evident that even the asset management sector’s leading lights on RI must build on their commitments to address issues like climate change. They can do this by taking a more systematic and science-based approach to integrating natural capital risks into investment decisions, which must involve setting portfolio-level targets on sustainability that are forward-looking, science-based, and time-bound.
Brian Rice, Portfolio Manager at CalSTRS, said “We expect our external asset managers to be integrating ESG analysis into investment decision-making. Included in this analysis is addressing natural capital risk exposure. WWF&apos;s recently launched RESPOND framework and tool provide new perspectives into natural capital risk that can be used to help inform asset managers’ decision making.”
The findings highlight the urgency with which other asset managers, especially those investing in Asia, must enhance their RI capabilities in order to position themselves competitively. To remain eligible for mandates and meet stakeholder expectations, it will also be essential for asset managers to enhance the transparency of their reporting.
About RESPOND
RESPOND (Resilient and Sustainable Portfolios that Protect Nature and Drive Decarbonization) is an interactive online tool developed by WWF to help asset managers improve portfolio resilience and alignment with a low carbon and sustainable future through the application of science-based approaches to responsible investment (RI). The tool allows users to explore how leading asset managers are implementing RI and also understand opportunities for further leadership. It is based on a WWF framework that represents a best-practice architecture for responsible investment and is aligned with the recommendations of the Task Force on Climate-related Financial Disclosures (TCFD) and the Principles for Responsible Investment (PRI).
This year’s RESPOND analysis is based on a WWF-led review of 22 leading asset managers’ English language public disclosures, released before 31 October 2019. Materials reviewed as a part of this analysis include the latest annual/sustainability/RI reports, public statements, investor presentations, press releases, and other information posted on asset managers’ websites, and PRI 2018 and 2019 Transparency reports. By using only publicly available information, RESPOND highlights the baseline level of information available to international asset owners, regulators and stakeholders seeking to understand how asset managers are addressing ESG risks and opportunities. Ahead of RESPOND’s launch, each asset manager included in the analysis was given the opportunity to review their preliminary results and provide feedback.
For more information please contact: 
Lilian Gikandi, Media Officer, WWF International, Email: lgikandi@wwfint.org +254 725 577 438
[1] Criteria for inclusion in the 2019 analysis were three-fold: a) asset managers with a minimum AUM of $200B, headquartered in Europe; b) asset managers that disclosed receiving a rating of A+ on either the Strategy &amp; Governance or Listed Equity modules of the PRI Reporting Framework in 2018 or 2019; and c) asset managers with a presence in Asia. Full details and rationale available here.
Key Findings
Light Blue: Range (min and max) for percentage of sub-indicators disclosed, by pillar
Dark Blue: Average percentage disclosure by pillar
</description>
<dc:date>2020-01-29T22:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Tam - the last male Sumatran rhino in Sabah dies</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=347692</link>
<description> “The world has lost yet another magnificent creature and moves closer towards losing an ancient rhino lineage. Teetering on the edge of extinction, the Sumatran rhino is considered the most endangered large mammal on earth. The death of this rhino underscores the critical importance of the collaborative efforts being driven by the Sumatran Rhino Rescue project. We offer our condolences to the Government of Sabah and the Borneo Rhino Alliance team, who cared for Tam in his final years.” said Dr. Margaret Kinnaird, of WWF.
“The death of Tam, the last known male Sumatran rhino in Malaysia, should remind us that if we don’t act quickly and boldly, we could lose the Sumatran rhino in our lifetime,” said Jon Paul Rodriguez, Chair of the International Union for Conservation of Nature Species Survival Commission.
It is believed that no more than 80 Sumatran rhinos remain, almost all on the island of Sumatra in Indonesia. After decades of poaching and habitat loss, the greatest threat now facing the species is the distance that separates their small populations. A tiny population of rhinos of the same subspecies as Tam clings to existence in central Borneo. The Government of Indonesia and an alliance of conservation organizations and on-the-ground experts known as the Sumatran Rhino Rescue have launched a focused and ambitious international effort to bring the Sumatran rhino back from the brink of extinction. The alliance is currently focused on finding and safely relocating the remaining scattered individuals to specialized facilities designed for their care with the hopes of eventually increasing their populations to numbers that allow them to be returned to the wild. </description>
<dc:date>2019-05-28T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Landmark documentary series Our Planet highlights need for global action to protect nature, says WWF</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=345490</link>
<description> As the long-awaited eight-part documentary series Our Planet, voiced by Sir David Attenborough, becomes available on Netflix globally today, a new survey[1] for the conservation organisation shows that only half (49% ) of people across 10 of the world’s most biodiverse countries are very convinced biodiversity -- our ‘safety net’ or ‘web of life’ -- is in decline. Just 39% realise that we depend on nature and biodiversity for key elements of life, such as food, water and clean air. 
WWF is calling on the public to stand up for the planet and is asking global leaders to address our nature emergency by working together to develop a global plan of action, a New Deal for Nature and People.
Despite the lack of widespread awareness of the crisis our planet is facing, the survey showed a majority of respondents (70%) across the 10 countries feel personally responsible for protecting nature and biodiversity. 65% say commitment from their governments to protect it is insufficient. The importance of protecting biodiversity for future generations is also considered as crucial to the majority (80%), while climate change, deforestation, and river and ocean pollution are seen as biodiversity’s biggest threats.
The figures highlight the importance of the global conversation that is being sparked by the ground breaking Our Planet Netflix series, created in collaboration with WWF and produced by Silverback Films, and aiming to reach millions of people to create a pivotal moment for nature. Thousands of people all over the world are adding their voices and calling for action via an online spinning globe demonstrating the scale of the movement worldwide. Go to www.ourplanet.com/voice/.
WWF Ambassador and naturalist Sir David Attenborough who narrates the series said: “Today we have become the greatest threat to the health of our home but there’s still time for us to address the challenges we’ve created, if we act now. If people can truly understand what is at stake, I believe they will expect business and governments to get on with the practical solutions.
And as a species we are expert problem-solvers. But we haven’t yet applied ourselves to this problem with the focus it requires. We can create a world with clean air and water, unlimited energy, and fish stocks that will sustain us well into the future.”
The Our Planet project launches at a critical time when our nature and wildlife is under threat like never before. Recent figures[2] from WWF’s Living Planet Report 2018 show that global populations of vertebrate species have, on average, declined by 60 per cent since 1970 – less than a lifetime.
Colin Butfield, Executive Director of WWF-UK and Conservation Advisor for Our Planet, said: “ We’re the first generation to know the full impact of what we’re doing to our planet, and the last that has the chance to do anything about it. If people around the world speak out and say our planet is worth protecting, our leaders will have no choice but to listen. We hope Our Planet will spark one of the most important conversations of our time - about the one home we all share.”
Through the series and WWF Our Planet initiatives, the charity is taking the opportunity to raise awareness, educate, and shift attitudes towards conservation. An array of free online resources at OurPlanet.com have been created to help people of all ages understand the importance of Earth’s habitats and how they can help safeguard them for people and wildlife for generations to come. The website is focused around the eight biomes introduced in the series and enables visitors to take a deep dive into the most pressing challenges and solutions facing our natural world.
OurPlanet.com will also provide a wealth of educational resources for schools, youth groups and families to engage young people in the global conversation around the series. These include downloadable classroom materials and guides for educators, an ‘Our Planet Live’ platform offering live link-ups with experts for classrooms all around the world, and a ground-breaking free nature ID app called Seek, developed for Our Planet by iNaturalist, which helps budding naturalists to gain a better understanding of their local environment and global biodiversity.
Visit OurPlanet.com to view the ‘How Biodiversity Works’ film to find out more about why it’s so important to our planet. 
Go to OurPlanet.com to go behind-the-scenes of the Our Planet Netflix series and find out how you can help our planet to thrive again by adding your voice calling for urgent action, make a pledge, and be part of an interactive journey exploring our astonishing planet through an explorable globe.
Follow Our Planet on Instagram, Twitter and Facebook and be part of the conversation with #ShareOurPlanet:
● Our Planet Instagram: www.instagram.com/ourplanet
● Our Planet Facebook: www.facebook.com/ourplanet
● Our Planet Twitter: www.twitter.com/ourplanet
- Ends -
Notes to Editors:
1 The Living Planet Report 2018, Nov 2018
2 Online survey on biodiversity across 10 countries, 18+ year olds, fieldwork conducted 3 - 13th Mar 18. 10,328 respondents. Countries include: China, India, Indonesia, Vietnam, Brazil, Columbia, Peru, Mexico, South Africa and Kenya.
About the New Deal for Nature and People:
In 2020 we have the chance to put the world on the path to a better future, due to a historic coming together of key international decisions on environment, climate and sustainable development that have the potential to put our planet at the heart of our economic, political and financial systems. This is an unmissable, one-off opportunity for world leaders to take action for our planet and to move us towards a better future that benefits everyone. A New Deal for Nature and People is urgently needed with the aim of reversing the trend of nature loss by 2030 and restoring nature.
About the Netflix Our Planet series
The series launches on 5 April 2019, showcasing the extraordinary place we all call home. From the creator of Planet Earth, Silverback Films and in collaboration with WWF, the eight-part series features never-before-seen footage of wildlife and their habitats while also revealing why the natural world matters to us all and what steps must be taken to preserve it.
The ambitious four-year Our Planet project has been filmed in 50 countries across all the continents of the world, with over 600 members of crew capturing more than three and a half thousand filming days, and will focus on the breadth of the diversity of habitats around the world, from the remote Arctic wilderness and mysterious deep oceans to the vast landscapes of Africa and diverse jungles of South America.
In the first episode, “One Planet,” viewers will travel from the Brazilian rainforest to Norway’s Svalbard archipelago, discovering how each fragile habitat is connected and why they are all essential for life to thrive on this planet. Subsequent episodes capture Earth’s key biomes, or habitats: the icy frozen worlds, jungles, coastal seas, deserts and grasslands, high seas, freshwater regions and forests. 
Thanks to an extensive team that includes some of the world’s best wildlife cinematographers, researchers and scientists — and the latest in 4K camera technology — each episode features several stunning sequences that have never been filmed before.
Unprecedented in scope and ambition, Our Planet will entertain and captivate a global audience of all ages. Our Planet is produced by Silverback Films, Ltd. Series producers are Alastair Fothergill and Keith Scholey.
The series is live on Netflix, go to Netflix.com/OurPlanet. The series promotes the shared responsibility we all have to protect the health of our home, highlighting that we may be the last generation that has the chance to address the challenges humankind has created.
</description>
<dc:date>2019-04-05T08:01:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Landmark documentary series Our Planet highlights need for global action to protect nature, says WWF</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=345490</link>
<description> As the long-awaited eight-part documentary series Our Planet, voiced by Sir David Attenborough, becomes available on Netflix globally today, a new survey[1] for the conservation organisation shows that only half (49% ) of people across 10 of the world’s most biodiverse countries are very convinced biodiversity -- our ‘safety net’ or ‘web of life’ -- is in decline. Just 39% realise that we depend on nature and biodiversity for key elements of life, such as food, water and clean air. 
WWF is calling on the public to stand up for the planet and is asking global leaders to address our nature emergency by working together to develop a global plan of action, a New Deal for Nature and People.
Despite the lack of widespread awareness of the crisis our planet is facing, the survey showed a majority of respondents (70%) across the 10 countries feel personally responsible for protecting nature and biodiversity. 65% say commitment from their governments to protect it is insufficient. The importance of protecting biodiversity for future generations is also considered as crucial to the majority (80%), while climate change, deforestation, and river and ocean pollution are seen as biodiversity’s biggest threats.
The figures highlight the importance of the global conversation that is being sparked by the ground breaking Our Planet Netflix series, created in collaboration with WWF and produced by Silverback Films, and aiming to reach millions of people to create a pivotal moment for nature. Thousands of people all over the world are adding their voices and calling for action via an online spinning globe demonstrating the scale of the movement worldwide. Go to www.ourplanet.com/voice/.
WWF Ambassador and naturalist Sir David Attenborough who narrates the series said: “Today we have become the greatest threat to the health of our home but there’s still time for us to address the challenges we’ve created, if we act now. If people can truly understand what is at stake, I believe they will expect business and governments to get on with the practical solutions.
And as a species we are expert problem-solvers. But we haven’t yet applied ourselves to this problem with the focus it requires. We can create a world with clean air and water, unlimited energy, and fish stocks that will sustain us well into the future.”
The Our Planet project launches at a critical time when our nature and wildlife is under threat like never before. Recent figures[2] from WWF’s Living Planet Report 2018 show that global populations of vertebrate species have, on average, declined by 60 per cent since 1970 – less than a lifetime.
Colin Butfield, Executive Director of WWF-UK and Conservation Advisor for Our Planet, said: “ We’re the first generation to know the full impact of what we’re doing to our planet, and the last that has the chance to do anything about it. If people around the world speak out and say our planet is worth protecting, our leaders will have no choice but to listen. We hope Our Planet will spark one of the most important conversations of our time - about the one home we all share.”
Through the series and WWF Our Planet initiatives, the charity is taking the opportunity to raise awareness, educate, and shift attitudes towards conservation. An array of free online resources at OurPlanet.com have been created to help people of all ages understand the importance of Earth’s habitats and how they can help safeguard them for people and wildlife for generations to come. The website is focused around the eight biomes introduced in the series and enables visitors to take a deep dive into the most pressing challenges and solutions facing our natural world.
OurPlanet.com will also provide a wealth of educational resources for schools, youth groups and families to engage young people in the global conversation around the series. These include downloadable classroom materials and guides for educators, an ‘Our Planet Live’ platform offering live link-ups with experts for classrooms all around the world, and a ground-breaking free nature ID app called Seek, developed for Our Planet by iNaturalist, which helps budding naturalists to gain a better understanding of their local environment and global biodiversity.
Visit OurPlanet.com to view the ‘How Biodiversity Works’ film to find out more about why it’s so important to our planet. 
Go to OurPlanet.com to go behind-the-scenes of the Our Planet Netflix series and find out how you can help our planet to thrive again by adding your voice calling for urgent action, make a pledge, and be part of an interactive journey exploring our astonishing planet through an explorable globe.
Follow Our Planet on Instagram, Twitter and Facebook and be part of the conversation with #ShareOurPlanet:
● Our Planet Instagram: www.instagram.com/ourplanet
● Our Planet Facebook: www.facebook.com/ourplanet
● Our Planet Twitter: www.twitter.com/ourplanet
- Ends -
Notes to Editors:
1 The Living Planet Report 2018, Nov 2018
2 Online survey on biodiversity across 10 countries, 18+ year olds, fieldwork conducted 3 - 13th Mar 18. 10,328 respondents. Countries include: China, India, Indonesia, Vietnam, Brazil, Columbia, Peru, Mexico, South Africa and Kenya.
About the New Deal for Nature and People:
In 2020 we have the chance to put the world on the path to a better future, due to a historic coming together of key international decisions on environment, climate and sustainable development that have the potential to put our planet at the heart of our economic, political and financial systems. This is an unmissable, one-off opportunity for world leaders to take action for our planet and to move us towards a better future that benefits everyone. A New Deal for Nature and People is urgently needed with the aim of reversing the trend of nature loss by 2030 and restoring nature.
About the Netflix Our Planet series
The series launches on 5 April 2019, showcasing the extraordinary place we all call home. From the creator of Planet Earth, Silverback Films and in collaboration with WWF, the eight-part series features never-before-seen footage of wildlife and their habitats while also revealing why the natural world matters to us all and what steps must be taken to preserve it.
The ambitious four-year Our Planet project has been filmed in 50 countries across all the continents of the world, with over 600 members of crew capturing more than three and a half thousand filming days, and will focus on the breadth of the diversity of habitats around the world, from the remote Arctic wilderness and mysterious deep oceans to the vast landscapes of Africa and diverse jungles of South America.
In the first episode, “One Planet,” viewers will travel from the Brazilian rainforest to Norway’s Svalbard archipelago, discovering how each fragile habitat is connected and why they are all essential for life to thrive on this planet. Subsequent episodes capture Earth’s key biomes, or habitats: the icy frozen worlds, jungles, coastal seas, deserts and grasslands, high seas, freshwater regions and forests. 
Thanks to an extensive team that includes some of the world’s best wildlife cinematographers, researchers and scientists — and the latest in 4K camera technology — each episode features several stunning sequences that have never been filmed before.
Unprecedented in scope and ambition, Our Planet will entertain and captivate a global audience of all ages. Our Planet is produced by Silverback Films, Ltd. Series producers are Alastair Fothergill and Keith Scholey.
The series is live on Netflix, go to Netflix.com/OurPlanet. The series promotes the shared responsibility we all have to protect the health of our home, highlighting that we may be the last generation that has the chance to address the challenges humankind has created.
</description>
<dc:date>2019-04-05T08:01:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>China joins African countries in efforts to curb wildlife trafficking</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=345134</link>
<description> Nairobi, Kenya and Gaborone, Botswana, 27 March 2019:China’s National Forestry and Grassland Administration (NFGA) and World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF), supported by the Chinese Embassies in Nairobi and Gaborone has concluded two advocacy workshops raising awareness on wildlife trafficking amongst Chinese nationals living and working in Kenya and Botswana.
The two workshops which took place on 25 March in Nairobi and 27 March in Gaborone respectively were attended by more than 200Chinese nationals working in State-owned enterprises, private businesses and residing in the two countries. Local wildlife conservation authorities and both local and international media were also present.
These workshops follow bilateral meetings between China’s president Xi and the two African leaders, Kenya’s President Uhuru Kenyatta and Botswana’s President Mokgweetsi Masisi respectively, during the 2018 Beijing Summit of the Forum on China-Africa Cooperation (FOCAC) in September where the three Heads of State committed themselves to enhancing cooperation across various sectors including wildlife conservation.
Chinese citizens are among the large number of global tourists who visit Kenya each year to witness the seasonal migration of wild animals across the Maasai Mara grasslands, home to over 20 migratory species, including the African Elephant. Kenya and China recently collaborated on the Nairobi-Mombasa Madaraka Express Railway, Kenya’s biggest infrastructure project since its independence, which also represents an important component of China’s Belt and Road Initiative.
Botswana is home to about 130,000 elephants based on its latest survey in 2014, conducted jointly by Elephants Without Borders and Botswana’s Department of Wildlife and National Parks (DWNP).
With the recent expansion of Chinese investment in Africa, incidences of ivory smuggling involving Chinese nationals continue to be reported with serious reputational risks for China internationally. The strengthening of laws to address illegal wildlife trade and the imposition of increasingly tougher penalties by many African Local governments has meant that Chinese citizens based in these countries need to be more aware of these regulations and the consequences of engaging in wildlife crimes.
In his opening statement, Peng Youdong, Deputy Minister of NFGA in China condemned the recent spike in poaching and smuggling activities targeting various species including: African elephants, rhinos, pangolins and rare timbers, which he said has become an issue of global concern. He said China’s recent decision to close its domestic ivory market, to ban the commercial processing of rhino horn and tiger bone, as well as its tightening of legislation governing the trade in other endangered wildlife species demonstrates the government’s commitment to tackling illegal wildlife trade.
The government is now stepping up its enforcement efforts to ensure these important legislative changes bear fruit. This includes intensified monitoring of its markets, crucial transport links and increasing border inspection. This workshop is also part of the Chinese government long-term strategy to educate its citizens living and working in Africa to ensure they adhere to the international laws governing the trade in wildlife and on becoming model citizens abroad.
The representative of China’s CITES[1] MA spoke about China’s implementation of CITES, and highlighted the implications of the Chinese domestic ivory trade ban and domestic legislation on wildlife protection. They also presented the management efforts made by the Chinese government to protect wild animals and plants.
WWF spoke about trends in African Elephant and rhino poaching and the associated illegal ivory and rhino horn trade. It noted that those convicted of wildlife crime faced harsh penalties in many African countries. Kenya, Tanzania and Ethiopia have all recently strengthened their penalties.
Wang Xuezheng, Counselor of the Embassy of China in Kenya, said: “The Chinese government has implemented a total ban on domestic commercial processing and sales of ivory and products, it is a sign of China&apos;s growing role of combating illegal ivory trade. Wildlife conservation has always been a key area of collaboration between China and Kenya. In 2014, law enforcement officers from the two countries jointly dismantled a criminal syndicate involved in ivory smuggling. In 2015, China donated wildlife protection equipment worth USD$537,000 to Kenya Wildlife Service. During the recent construction of Nairobi-Mombasa Madaraka Express Railway, Chinese companies invested heavily in preserving critical wildlife corridors by buildinghundreds of tunnels, culverts and bridges to allow safe passage for wildlife acrosshabitats.”
Zhao Yanbo, Ambassador of the Embassy of China in Botswana, said: “The Chinese government has been actively supporting Botswana&apos;s wildlife protection work. In 2016, equipment and materials worth CNY 10 million (USD 1.5 million) were donated to Botswana for wildlife conservation and forest law enforcement. I hope that Chinese nationals in Botswana will learn and adhere to the laws and policies governing illegal wildlife trade and wildlife conservation and spread the word to their fellow Chinese residing here.”
&quot;Legal ivory is no longer available in China. In addition, any attempt to bring ivory from abroad is illegal and will be punished by law,” said Zhou Fei, Chief Programme Officer of WWF China, “Ivory or rhino horn items are simply not options as souvenir or gifts for international travelers.”
During the visits, constructive bilateral consultations also took place between China’s National Forestry and Grassland Administration and their counterparts in Kenya and Botswana respectively. Both sides recognized their shared responsibility in ensuring compliance with CITES regulations and agreed to strengthen information exchange and wildlife conservation advocacy to prevent the poaching and smuggling of illegal wildlife products.
At the end of the workshop, a public pledge to say no to illegal wildlife trade was made by the representatives of the local Chinese nationals and companies in Kenya and Botswana.
This was the 15th outreach workshop of its kind jointly conducted by WWF and NFGA in collaboration with various Chinese Embassies in Africa.
[1] Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora.
Note to Editors:
Among those who attended the workshops are:
Peng Youdong, Deputy Minister of NFGA in China; Wang Xuezheng, Counselor of the Embassy of China in Kenya; Dr. Patrick Omondi, Ag. Director Biodiversity, Research &amp; Planning of Kenya Wildlife Service; Zhao Yanbo, Ambassador of the Embassy of China in Botswana; and Thato Yaone Raphaka,Permanent Secretary, Ministry of Environment, Natural Resource Conservation and Tourism.
Zhou Fei, Chief Programme Officer of WWF China and Dr Margaret Kinnaird, Global Wildlife Practice Leader made the opening remarks on behalf of WWF. Dr. Meng Xianlin, Director General of NFGA’s International Cooperation Department hosted both workshops. </description>
<dc:date>2019-03-28T00:00:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>World leaders fail to address plastic crisis</title>
<link>https://wwf.panda.org/?uNewsID=344654</link>
<description> The Fourth United Nations Environment Assembly (UNEA-4), which took place from 11-15 March, ended with no agreement on starting a process towards a global, legally binding deal on marine plastics pollution - a solution advocated by WWF.
A WWF report launched on 5 March warned that without a drastic change in approach, global plastic pollution will continue to worsen, with 104 million metric tons of plastic at risk of leaking into the planet’s ecosystems by 2030. 
“Over eight million tonnes of plastic is dumped into the oceans every year. UNEA-4 was an opportunity for the world’s leaders to make serious and tangible commitments and pledges to combating this global crisis,” said Marco Lambertini, WWF International’s Director General.
“This crisis cannot wait another two years for the next round of UNEA talks. We are urging all supportive countries to use this disappointing outcome to accelerate their work towards a global binding agreement on marine plastic pollution.”
More than 300,000 people have so far joined WWF’s global petition calling for a legally binding deal on marine plastics pollution.
</description>
<dc:date>2019-03-15T17:30:00Z</dc:date>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
